Register of the Leo Eloesser Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Leo Eloesser Papers
1861-1994
2003C44
Eloesser, Leo.
50 boxes, 1 oversize folder, 2 art works (30.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs and other writings, correspondence, reports, clippings, other printed matter, photographs, motion picture film, memorabilia, and miscellany, relating to international medical aid to Spain during the Spanish Civil War, international medical aid to China during the Sino-Japanese War and Chinese Civil War, and medical practice in the United States, Mexico and elsewhere. Includes some papers of Joyce Campbell, companion of Leo Eloesser.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
One amateur painting, China, undated, restricted due to extremely fragile condition.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2003.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1918 Works as a U.S. Army surgeon at Letterman Hospital, San Francisco
1919 Returns to City and County Hospital of San Francisco
1920s Studies advanced medicine in Germany and Austria
1935 Visits Japan and the Soviet Union
1937-1938 Works as a medical volunteer on the Republican side during the Spanish Civil War
1943-1945 Travels in Latin America, giving lectures and attending conferences in Argentine, Chile, and Cuba
1945-1949 Works as a doctor in China for the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) and the United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF), training medical personnel
1950s Meets Joyce Campbell, and moves with her to Mexico, establishing a ranch near Tacámbaro, Michoacán
1950s-1960s Travels extensively and is involved in the promotion of rural health care programs in underdeveloped countries. Writes and lectures on the treatment of tuberculosis
1955 Pregnancy, Childbirth and the Newborn, a training manual for rural midwives
1973 Visits the People's Republic of China and meets with medical colleagues
1976 Dies
2004 Joyce Campbell dies
Scope and Content of Collection
The Leo Eloesser papers in the Hoover Institution Archives document the life and work of a medical pioneer with strong ties to both Stanford and San Francisco, and of a man who also gained recognition for his humanitarian efforts around the world. Additionally, the papers contain substantial materials relating to the life of Eloesser's companion, Joyce Campbell, and to Eloesser and Campbell's years together in Mexico.
Leo Eloesser trained as a physician specializing in thoracic surgery in both the United States and Europe, and gained experience in the treatment of war casualties during World War I. He later became a prominent expert in the treatment and prevention of tuberculosis. Eloesser published many writings on a wide variety of medical subjects, and these can be found in the Speeches and Writings series of the papers.
In 1937, Eloesser volunteered his services as a doctor on behalf of Republican forces during the Spanish Civil War, and he was present on the Teruel front during heavy fighting there in 1938. While in Spain, Eloesser wrote several articles for American publications describing his experiences, and these and other related documents are contained in the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy the papers.
Following World War II, Eloesser became involved in medical relief work conducted in China by the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration and, subsequently, the United Nations Children's Fund. In the midst of the civil war between Communist and Nationalist forces, Eloesser instructed medical personnel in first aid, midwifery, and general health care. Eloesser's correspondence and reports from this period, along with instructional materials used in his training courses, can be found in the UNRRA/UNICEF file in the papers.
From his work in China, Eloesser became interested in devising basic medical programs to help the rural poor in underdeveloped countries. He published a textbook for rural midwives in 1955, and throughout the 1950s and 1960s was active in the fight against tuberculosis in Latin America.
Eloesser spent the latter part of his life on a ranch in Mexico, which he ran with Joyce Campbell. This period is extensively documented in the Correspondence series, especially in Eloesser's many letters to Campbell. Joyce Campbell's life is recorded in the Joyce Campbell Series, which includes her correspondence with Eloesser and many other individuals.
The papers contain an extensive Photographs series, with numerous prints dating from Eloesser's time in China, and others dating from his many working visits to countries besides China. These prints often depict Eloesser in the company of his medical peers.
Among Eloesser's friends were prominent artists, including Diego Rivera, Frida Kahlo, and the American sculptor Ralph Stackpole. In the Photographs series of the papers there are numerous prints depicting Diego Rivera murals, and there are clippings about Rivera's life in the Subject File of the papers. The Subject File also contains important materials relating to the case of Tom Mooney, a political cause célèbre of the American left before World War II. These materials include the autopsy report on Mooney prepared by Eloesser.
On his many travels, Eloesser collected examples of local art and literature, and there are important works of art from Latin America and China in the papers. The Printed Matter series includes a collection of Brazilian chapbooks with woodcut illustrations; the Oversize Materials series contains numerous Chinese art works and several important paintings from Latin American artists.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into fourteen series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy File, UNRRA/UNICEF File, Joyce Campbell Series, Subject File, Photographs, Motion Pictures, Art Works, Printed Matter, and Oversize Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Medical assistance--China.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; China--History--Civil War, 1945-1949.; Medical assistance--Spain.; Campbell, Joyce.
Genre
Moving-pictures.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1861-1983. (Box 1)
  Address books, application, articles, chronologies, clippings, curriculum vitae, invitations, list of publications, monograph, obituary, oral histories, papers, passports, programs, and visas, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address books, undated (Box 1: 1)
  - Application by Eloesser for Mexican citizenship, 1955-1978. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes application, 1955, and related correspondence, 1955-1978
  - Articles from medical journals about Eloesser, 1943-1975. (Folder 1: 3)
    Printed copies
  - Chronologies of Eloesser's travels, 1945-1949. (Folder 1: 4)
    Holographs
  - Clippings, largely relating to Eloesser's career as a medical doctor
    - 1903-1938 (Folder 1: 5)
    - 1941-1943 (Folder 1: 6)
    - 1944-1947 (Folder 1: 7)
    - 1948-1949 (Folder 1: 8)
    - 1950-1955 (Folder 1: 9)
    - 1956-1983 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1962 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Family papers, 1861-1918. (Folder 2: 3)
    Includes copy of father's will and grandfather's life insurance policy
  - Health certificates, 1951-1961 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Honorary diplomas, 1951-1957 (Folder 2: 5)
  - List of publications, undated (Folder 2: 6)
  - Medical school records, 1901-1905 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Monograph, 1976. (Folder 2: 8)
    Printed copy of Surgery by Francis D. Moore, with passage concerning Eloesser
  - Obituary, 1976. (Folder 2: 9)
    Printed copy
  - Oral histories, 1968-1970. (Folder 2: 10)
    Transcripts of interviews with Eloesser conducted in 1968 by Ruth Newhall and Russel V. Lee. Includes related correspondence
  - Passports, 1949-1962 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Programs and invitations, 1938-1976 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Testimonial speech in honor of Eloesser, 1952. (Folder 2: 13)
    Typescript
  - Visas and travel documents, 1943-1965 (Folder 2: 14)
- Correspondence, 1903-1976.
  Cards, enclosures, and letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - Christmas cards, 1938-1971 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Letters of recommendation, 1943-1973 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Unidentified, 1903-1976 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Abrams, Herbert K., 1973-1975 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Alarcón, Donato G., 1955-1966 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Almy, Thomas, 1952 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Alvarez, Hector, 1966-1968 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Alvizouri, Mario, 1968 (Folder 2: 22)
  - American Association for Thoracic Surgery (Thomas H. Burford, Thomas B. Ferguson, Hiram Langston, Richard H. Meade, Jr.), 1947-1970 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - American Bureau for Medical Aid to China, Inc. (Adele B. Cohn, Maxwell M. Hamilton, Helen Kennedy Stevens, Co Tui), 1941-1942 (Folder 3: 2)
- Bacon, Ernest, 1945 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Baldó, José Ignacio, 1959-1967 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Bastos Ansart, Manuel, 1949 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Betts, Reeve H., 1956 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Blumenfeld, Margaret, undated (Folder 3: 7)
  - Borcic, B., 1953 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Bowles, Newton Rowell, 1956-1976 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Brewer, Lyman, III, 1975 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Bustamante, Miguel E., 1972 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Camishion, Rudolph C., 1966 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Campbell, Joyce
    - 1951-1952 (Folder 3: 13)
    - 1953 (Folder 3: 14)
    - 1954-1955 (Folder 3: 15)
    - 1956 (Folder 3: 16)
    - 1966 (Folder 3: 17)
    - 1970 (Folder 3: 18)
    - 1972 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Campillo Sainz, Carlos, 1969-1973 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Chacon, Roberto, 1903-1909 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Chandler, L. R., 1947 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Cook, Joseph A., 1968 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Costero, Isaac, 1967 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Curry, Francis J., 1975 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Dean, Mallette, 1968 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Dock, Bill and Maria, 1947-1966 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Domínguez, Adolfo, 1958 (Folder 3: 28)
  - Eggers, Carl, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Eloesser, Alice, 1915-1929 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Eloesser, Arthur, Mr. and Mrs., 1903-1922 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Eloesser, Herbert, 1945-1947 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Etchegary, Fernando, 1944 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Fairley, Lincoln, 1970-1975 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Forbes, Helen, 1936 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Freeman, Paul, 1971 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Galt, Edith, 1950 (Folder 4: 9)
  - García-Rosell, Ovidio, 1966 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Garland, L. Henry, 1961 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Gibbon, John H., Jr., 1966 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Gutierrez, Elihu J., 1954-1958 (Folder 4: 13)
  - Hartman, Ferris, 1965-1966 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Hatem, George (Ma Hai Teh), 1973-1975 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Hemingway, Isabel, 1950-1974 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Herbert, L. M., 1976 (Folder 4: 17)
  - Howell, W. M., undated (Folder 4: 18)
  - Humphreys, George H., II, 1967 (Folder 4: 19)
  - Ingram, Ruth, 1949-1964. (Folder 4: 20)
    Includes typescript of Ingram's account of her time in China with Eloesser
  - Instituto Indigenista Interamericano (Gonzalo Rubio Orbe, D. Demetrio Sodi), 1973 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Ivanissevich, Oscar, 1943 (Folder 4: 22)
  - Jacob, Phil and Betty, 1956-1966 (Folder 4: 23)
  - James, Carl, 1963 (Folder 4: 24)
  - Jimenez, Miguel, 1973 (Folder 4: 25)
  - Jones, Wilfred M. G., 1954 (Folder 4: 26)
  - Journal of the American Medical Association, 1960 (Folder 4: 27)
  - Kahlo, Cristina, 1963 (Folder 4: 28)
  - Kemeny, John, 1963 (Folder 4: 29)
  - Kramer, Herman P., 1957 (Folder 4: 30)
  - LaPlant, Helen, 1931-1949 (Folder 4: 31)
  - Leaumax, Joey Guerrero, 1947-1970. (Folder 4: 32)
    Includes related correspondence with Frederick D. Bauschard, Herman H. Hilleboe, Albert O'Hara, and Ralph C. Williams
  - Lee, Philip R., 1963 (Folder 4: 33)
  - Lee, Russel V., 1960-1972 (Folder 4: 34)
  - Lepădat, Petre, 1977 (Folder 4: 35)
  - Lester, Charles W., 1967-1969 (Folder 4: 36)
  - Li, An-che, 1947 (Folder 4: 37)
  - Limon G., Eduardo, 1975 (Folder 4: 38)
  - Manson, Clara, 1972 (Folder 4: 39)
  - Markings, Yay, 1947 (Folder 4: 40)
  - Martin, Alice E., 1971 (Folder 4: 41)
  - McNutt, Frank and Becky, 1973-1974 (Folder 4: 42)
  - Meyer-Levy, Claude, 1971 (Folder 4: 43)
  - Michael, C. E., Mr. and Mrs., 1950 (Folder 4: 44)
  - Milhaud, Darius, 1963 (Folder 4: 45)
  - Monge M., Carlos, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Moore, Francis D., 1975 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Muñoz Marín, Inés M. de, 1958 (Folder 5: 3)
  - Newhall, Ruth and Scott, 1963-1972 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Noble, Carlos, 1955 (Folder 5: 5)
  - Norris, Kathleen, undated (Folder 5: 6)
  - Oppenheim, Erich A., 1960 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Orrego Puelma, Héctor, 1975 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Ploch, Richard A., 1969 (Folder 5: 9)
  - La Prensa (Luis Martín), 1938 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Purdy, Ralph, 1945 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Quijano Pitman, Fernando, 1945 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Requena, Antonio, 1967 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Reynolds, Lloyd R., 1947 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Rhoads, Jonathan E., 1973 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Rogers, William Lister, 1966 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Roith, Otto, 1947 (Folder 5: 17)
  - Ronaghy, Hossain A., 1976 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Schmulowitz, Nat, 1956 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Shumacker, Harris B., Jr., 1961 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Simpson, Lesley Byrd, 1959 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Sleeper, James D., 1967 (Folder 5: 22)
  - Soong, Ching Ling, 1949 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Stackpole, Hebe, 1971 (Folder 5: 24)
  - Stackpole, Ralph, 1954 (Folder 5: 25)
  - Stackpole-Cuellar, Anne, undated (Folder 5: 26)
  - Staines, Enrique, 1954 (Folder 5: 27)
  - Szigeti, Joseph, 1968 (Folder 5: 28)
  - Thomas, Lucius G., 1956 (Folder 5: 29)
  - Tresidder, Donald B., 1946 (Folder 5: 30)
  - United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF), 1973 (Folder 5: 31)
  - United States Department of Labor (Arthur L. Schoenthal), 1955 (Folder 5: 32)
  - United States Public Health Service (L. F. Badger), 1946 (Folder 5: 33)
  - Urteaga Ballon, Oscar, 1966 (Folder 5: 34)
  - Velasco Suarez, Manuel, 1976 (Folder 5: 35)
  - Wallace, Kevin, undated (Folder 5: 36)
  - Weiss, Pedro, 1966 (Folder 5: 37)
  - Wood, David A., 1967 (Folder 5: 38)
- Correspondence, 1899-1976.
  Articles, conference papers, monograph, resolution, and speeches, arranged chronologically
  - "Aneurysm of the Common Iliac Artery: Gradual Occlusion by Ligation with a Free Graft of Muscle,", undated (Folder 5: 39)
  - "Apuntes sobre Luis Enrique Erro, un moderno Leonardo da Vinci,", undated. (Folder 5: 40)
  - Autobiographical writing, undated. (Folder 5: 41)
    Holograph
  - "The Birth of Ski Sport in California,", undated. (Folder 5: 42)
  - "La colonia de tuberculosis en Baja California y su proyeccion en los programas de lucha antituberculosa de la zona noroeste de Mexico,", undated. (Folder 5: 43)
  - "Fracturas de los huesos de la pierna, su mecanismo y tratamiento," lecture, undated. (Folder 5: 44)
  - "Pathological Conditions in Pulmonary Tuberculosis Indicating Surgical Intervention and the Various Forms of Operation Applicable to Them,", undated. (Folder 5: 45)
  - "The Pathological Reminiscenses [sic] of Schwund,", undated. (Folder 5: 46)
  - "Progress of Surgery during the Last Decade,", undated. (Folder 5: 47)
  - "Realización de un proyecto para un hospital antituberculoso con colonias cooperativo-ejidales en el estado de Baja California" (with E. Gutiérrez), undated. (Folder 5: 48)
  - "V. Hirtel,", undated. (Folder 5: 49)
  - "Allgemeiner Cellen-Verein G. H. Schultze," The University of California Magazine, 1899 November. (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - "Letters from Europe,", 1901-1902. (Folder 6: 2)
    Typescript collection of letters sent by Eloesser to his family
  - "Stories and drawings,", 1904-1905. (Folder 6: 3)
  - "Obstetrical Play,", ca. 1905. (Folder 6: 4)
  - "Nasal Plastic, with Free Transplantation of Bone," California State Journal of Medicine, 1911 August. (Folder 6: 5)
  - "Recent Advances in Regional (Local) Anesthesia," California State Journal of Medicine, 1912 March. (Folder 6: 6)
  - "Implantation of Joints," California State Journal of Medicine, 1913 December. (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Local Anesthesia in Major Operations on the Head and Face," The Pacific Dental Gazette, 1914 February. (Folder 6: 8)
  - "Surgery of Peptic Ulcer," California State Journal of Medicine, 1914 September. (Folder 6: 9)
  - "Repair of Defects in Blood Vessels by Free Grafts of Fatty Tissue," The Journal of the American Medical Association, 1915 January 30. (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Amputations and Their After-Treatment," California State Journal of Medicine, 1915 December. (Folder 6: 11)
  - "Notes from a German Military Hospital, with Observations on Gas Phlegmons," The Journal of the American Medical Association, 1915 December 4. (Folder 6: 12)
  - Reprint comprising three articles, "Pathology of War Surgery with Reference to Its Relation to Diseases of the Mouth," "Gunshot Wounds and Lesions Produced by Shell and Shrapnel in the Jaws and Face," and "Plastic Surgery of the Jaws and Face: Bone Grafting in the Jaws," The Journal of the National Dental Association, vol. IV, nos. 10-12, 1917. (Folder 6: 13)
  - "Gunshot Wounds and Lesions Produced by Shell and Shrapnel in the Jaws and Face," lecture, San Francisco Section of the Preparedness League of American Dentists, 1917 May 8. (Folder 6: 14)
  - "Fractures in War Time," California State Journal of Medicine, 1917 July. (Folder 6: 15)
  - "On the Nature of Neuropathic Affections of the Joints,"Annals of Surgery, 1917 August. (Folder 6: 16)
  - "Wounds of the Joints," The Boston Medical and Surgical Journal, 1918 April 25. (Folder 6: 17)
  - "Rib Grafting Operations for the Repair of Bone Defects and Their End Results," Archives of Surgery, 1920 November. (Folder 6: 18)
  - "Leg Ulcer,", ca. 1921. (Folder 6: 19)
  - "On the Severely but Not Totally Disabled in Industry, with Special Reference to the One-Armed," The Boston Medical and Surgical Journal, 1921 May 12. (Folder 6: 20)
  - "A Sign Occurring in Case of Tabes Complicated by Charcot Joints," The Journal of the American Medical Association, 1921 August 20. (Folder 6: 21)
  - "Some Notes on Plastic Operations," Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 1922 April. (Folder 6: 22)
  - "Thoracoplastic Compression of the Lung in Pulmonary Tuberculosis," Archives of Internal Medicine, 1923 May. (Folder 6: 23)
  - "Local Anesthesia in Major Surgery: Its Uses and Limitations," California State Journal of Medicine, 1923 October. (Folder 6: 24)
  - "Surgical Intervention in Pulmonary Tuberculosis," The American Review of Tuberculosis, 1924 February. (Folder 6: 25)
  - "Primary Tumors of the Lung," Archives of Surgery, 1925 January. (Folder 6: 26)
  - "Intraplueral Pneumolysis,", ca. 1926. (Folder 6: 27)
  - "Pirate and Buccaneer Doctors," Annals of Medical History, vol. VIII, no. 1, 1926. (Folder 6: 28)
  - "Preliminary Artificial Pneumothorax in Operations on the Open Chest," Archives of Surgery, 1927 January. (Folder 6: 29)
  - "Congenital Cystic Disease of the Lung,", ca. 1928. (Folder 6: 30)
  - "Surgery of the Pleura" in The Thoracic Wall, Pleura and Lungs, ca. 1928. (Folder 6: 31)
  - "On Sites and Types of Amputation and Exarticulation together with Some Notes on Technic,", ca. 1929. (Folder 6: 32)
  - "Treatment of Bronchiectasis," Northwest Medicine, 1929 June. (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Closure of Bronchial Fistula,", ca. 1930 (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Meningopleural Fistula following Extirpation of a Ganglioneuroma of the Upper Mediastinum; Ganglioneuroma of the Adrenal Gland,", ca. 1931. (Folder 7: 3)
  - Bronchial Stenosis, 1932. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Subcostal Extrapleural Compression of the Lung," The Journal of Thoracic Surgery, 1932 August. (Folder 7: 5)
  - "Treatment of Fractures of the Upper End of the Humerus: An Experimental and Clinical Study," The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, 1934 January. (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Bronchial Stenosis in Pulmonary Tuberculosis," The American Review of Tuberculosis, 1934 August. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Chronic Bronchial Stenosis," International Clinics, vol. II, series 45, 1935. (Folder 7: 8)
  - "An Operation for Tuberculous Empyema," Surgery, Gynecology and Obstetrics, 1935 June. (Folder 7: 9)
  - "Dr. David Cohn (1837-1935)," Bulletin of the San Francisco County Medical Society, 1935 October. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "Blocked Cavities in Pulmonary Tuberculosis," The Journal of Thoracic Surgery, 1937 October. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "The Treatment of Some Abdominal Cancers by Irradiation through the Open Abdomen Combined with Cautery Incision," Annals of Surgery, 1937 October. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "A Model to Illustrate the Mechanics of Respiration and Movements of the Mediastinum with and without Various Kinds and Degrees of Bronchial Stenosis" (with Anthony Freeman), Surgery, 1938 May. (Folder 7: 13)
  - "Emmet Rixford, 1865-1938," Annals of Surgery, 1939 October. (Folder 7: 14)
  - "In Memoriam Norman Bethune, 1890-1939," The Journal of Thoracic Surgery, 1940 April. (Folder 7: 15)
  - "Treatment of Compound Fractures in War," The Journal of the American Medical Association, 1940 November 30. (Folder 7: 16)
  - "Transthoracic Bronchotomy for Removal of Benign Tumors of the Bronchi," Annals of Surgery, 1940 December. (Folder 7: 17)
  - "The Choice of Procedure in the Treatment of Turberculous Cavities," The Journal of Thoracic Surgery, 1941 June. (Folder 7: 18)
  - "An Operation for the Treatment of Apical Turberculous Cavities Persisting in an Artificial Pneumothorax" in Medical Tributes to Harold Brunn, 1942. (Folder 7: 19)
  - "Osteoplastic Thoracoplasty," The American Review of Tuberculosis, 1942 June. (Folder 7: 20)
  - Lecture, First Inter-American Congress of Surgery, Santiago de Chile, Chile, 1942 November. (Folder 7: 21)
    Correspondence and program only
  - Speech, Buenos Aires, Argentina, 1943 October 5. (Folder 7: 22)
  - Second Interamerican Congress of Surgery, Buenos Aires, Argentina, 1943 November
    - Correspondence (Folder 7: 23)
    - Itinerary (Folder 7: 24)
    - Lecture on lung cancer. (Folder 7: 25)
    - Report (Folder 7: 26)
    - Testimonials (Folder 7: 27)
  - "Treatment of Spontaneous Pneumothorax" (with E. R. Movitt and J. V. Smith), ca. 1944. (Folder 7: 28)
  - "Flap Drainage of Tuberculous and Non-Tuberculous Cavities" (with W. L. Rogers and S. J. Shipman) in Transactions of the Fortieth Annual Meeting of the National Tuberculosis Association, 1944. (Folder 7: 29)
    Printed copy of abstract only
  - "A Still for Providing Rural Districts with Distilled Water,", ca. 1947. (Folder 7: 30)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Dr. Harold Philips Hill,", 1947. (Folder 7: 31)
  - "A Pocket Guide to Treatment of Common Fractures, Dislocations and Head Injuries,", 1948
    - Correspondence (Folder 7: 32)
    - Typescripts
      - First draft (Folder 7: 33)
      - Second draft (Folder 7: 34)
  - "First Aid; Emergency Treatment of Injuries; Preparation of Dressings and Surgical Supplies,", 1949 January 29
    - Typescript (Folder 7: 35)
    - Corrections and revisions (Folder 7: 36)
  - "On Education of Subaltern Sanitary and Medical Personnel,", ca. 1950. (Folder 7: 37)